<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Qt on Daker Pinheiro</title>
    <link>https://dakerfp.com/tags/qt/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Qt on Daker Pinheiro</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Ⓒ 2017 Daker Fernandes Pinheiro</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://dakerfp.com/tags/qt/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Qt &amp; KDE in FISL 13</title>
      <link>https://dakerfp.com/post/qt-kde-in-fisl-13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dakerfp.com/post/qt-kde-in-fisl-13/</guid>
      <description>It was a great to see again some friends from KDE Brazil and met some new ones. The Konqui
I also gave some talks and workshop about Qt, KDE and game development.
Workshop: Developing applications for multiple devices using Plasma technologies This workshop was idealized and given by Sebas, and I was there to help him. In the workshop, QML was introduced together with KDE libs and what they can add to the applications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Akademy 2012</title>
      <link>https://dakerfp.com/post/akademy-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dakerfp.com/post/akademy-2012/</guid>
      <description>Hey folks, I&amp;rsquo;m going to Akademy!
I and Thiago are going to present Qt Components &amp;amp; Qt Styles in Qt5.
I hope to see you in Tallinn!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>QML Theming/Styling (Update)</title>
      <link>https://dakerfp.com/post/qml-themingstyling-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dakerfp.com/post/qml-themingstyling-update/</guid>
      <description>This post is an update about the research project from my team, described a few weeks ago.
From the time we published the last post about QML Styling until now we have worked on this set of issues/features:
 Get feedback about research project Combo Box Component Combo Box Customizable Style Combo Box Plastique Style SubControl Styling Understand SceneGraph internals Understand other native platform internals  I will detail what was possible to make for each of these topics in sessions below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Qt, KDE &amp; Akademy 2012 Event Guide Application</title>
      <link>https://dakerfp.com/post/qt-kde-akademy-2012-event-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dakerfp.com/post/qt-kde-akademy-2012-event-guide/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been away from KDE activities from a time, because I was organizing a lot of stuff in my life. Happily I&amp;rsquo;ve finally arranged some time to hack more on the weekends. I&amp;rsquo;ll try to keep up the work with the Plasma Components documentation, because I think it can be improved a lot. I will also try to come up with a few examples inside the documentation, to make easier for plasmoid developers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back to Plasma Components</title>
      <link>https://dakerfp.com/post/back_to_plasma_components/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dakerfp.com/post/back_to_plasma_components/</guid>
      <description>This last month I&amp;rsquo;ve been working slowly on my GSoC project due to the university activities (due to Brazilian academic calendar). And my thesis, which I shall talk in other post. But at least now I&amp;rsquo;m undergraduated!
As I explained in my last post about [Plasma Components], my GSoC project. I&amp;rsquo;m building graphics components for developers to build plasmoids in QML using non trivial common components such as Sliders, ScrollBars and RadioButtons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PySide at CITi</title>
      <link>https://dakerfp.com/post/pyside_at_citi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dakerfp.com/post/pyside_at_citi/</guid>
      <description>Here is the PySide slides from the python course at CITi. Have fun!
CITi - PySide</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>QtQuick - WSL II</title>
      <link>https://dakerfp.com/post/qtquick-wsl-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dakerfp.com/post/qtquick-wsl-ii/</guid>
      <description>QtQuick uses QML, a powerful tool for creating fluid interfaces in a clean, easy and fast way. It uses a declarative language (Javascript based) and it has a really good performance, which makes it suitable to make apps for any kind of platform. It&amp;rsquo;s also really easy to extend QML with Qt/C++, enbling developers to speedup the application logic or something else needed. Is also possible to use OpenGL to render QtQuick without any change in the code, sending the painting job to the video card.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>