<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cryptography on Daker Pinheiro</title>
    <link>https://dakerfp.com/tags/cryptography/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cryptography on Daker Pinheiro</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Ⓒ 2017 Daker Fernandes Pinheiro</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://dakerfp.com/tags/cryptography/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The ePassport Standard and it&#39;s Cryptographic Scheme</title>
      <link>https://dakerfp.com/post/the-epassport-standard-and-its-cryptographic-scheme/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dakerfp.com/post/the-epassport-standard-and-its-cryptographic-scheme/</guid>
      <description>ePassport is the name given for the new passport specification standardized by the International Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO). It was created to speed up and standardize the immigration procedures. This standard specifies RFID as the communication channel between the passport and the reader. The main feature present on it is the insertion of biometric data into the passport for biometric checks, including facial recognition, fingerprint and iris information. To keep this important data protected, an interesting cryptographic layer was added in addition to the usual document falsification mechanisms such as watermarks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Encrypted Tweets</title>
      <link>https://dakerfp.com/post/encrypted-tweets/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dakerfp.com/post/encrypted-tweets/</guid>
      <description>As a cryptography course project, me and @laisandrade developed a twitter extension which allows us to tweet in a way that only a group of followers can decrypt and understand my tweet. The goal is to secure broadcasting tweets to a group of followers and avoid anyone else to understand it&amp;rsquo;s content. This definition of security is safe against an eavesdropping attack, which is commonly considered secure for cryptography, what is not true.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>