<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Plasma on Daker Pinheiro</title>
    <link>https://dakerfp.com/tags/plasma/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Plasma on Daker Pinheiro</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Ⓒ 2017 Daker Fernandes Pinheiro</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://dakerfp.com/tags/plasma/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Qt &amp; KDE in FISL 13</title>
      <link>https://dakerfp.com/post/qt-kde-in-fisl-13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dakerfp.com/post/qt-kde-in-fisl-13/</guid>
      <description>It was a great to see again some friends from KDE Brazil and met some new ones. The Konqui
I also gave some talks and workshop about Qt, KDE and game development.
Workshop: Developing applications for multiple devices using Plasma technologies This workshop was idealized and given by Sebas, and I was there to help him. In the workshop, QML was introduced together with KDE libs and what they can add to the applications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Qt, KDE &amp; Akademy 2012 Event Guide Application</title>
      <link>https://dakerfp.com/post/qt-kde-akademy-2012-event-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dakerfp.com/post/qt-kde-akademy-2012-event-guide/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been away from KDE activities from a time, because I was organizing a lot of stuff in my life. Happily I&amp;rsquo;ve finally arranged some time to hack more on the weekends. I&amp;rsquo;ll try to keep up the work with the Plasma Components documentation, because I think it can be improved a lot. I will also try to come up with a few examples inside the documentation, to make easier for plasmoid developers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back to Plasma Components</title>
      <link>https://dakerfp.com/post/back_to_plasma_components/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dakerfp.com/post/back_to_plasma_components/</guid>
      <description>This last month I&amp;rsquo;ve been working slowly on my GSoC project due to the university activities (due to Brazilian academic calendar). And my thesis, which I shall talk in other post. But at least now I&amp;rsquo;m undergraduated!
As I explained in my last post about [Plasma Components], my GSoC project. I&amp;rsquo;m building graphics components for developers to build plasmoids in QML using non trivial common components such as Sliders, ScrollBars and RadioButtons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plasma Components</title>
      <link>https://dakerfp.com/post/plasma-components/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dakerfp.com/post/plasma-components/</guid>
      <description>Hi,
I will talk about my GSoC project (\m/), the plasma components. As you may know, QML is a declarative language to build rich interfaces introduced in Qt 4.7 by providing simple primitives. As it is a powerful way to develop interfaces and it&amp;rsquo;s the future of UI development for Qt was necessary to make the plasma support it.
Create interfaces in QML is really easy and fast but sometimes we need common widgets and may be boring to reimplement and replicate them in every application we create (e.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>