<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Machine learning on Daker Pinheiro</title>
    <link>https://dakerfp.com/tags/machine-learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Machine learning on Daker Pinheiro</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Ⓒ 2017 Daker Fernandes Pinheiro</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://dakerfp.com/tags/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Interfacing Keras with tensorflow</title>
      <link>https://dakerfp.com/post/keras-tensorflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dakerfp.com/post/keras-tensorflow/</guid>
      <description>Keras is great for machine learning and describing models! However, sometimes it lacks the flexibility power that Tensorflow has. The great news is that you can interface while using Tensorflow as a backend for Keras.
You may for instance, pre-process your data before feeding into a Keras learning model, to use GPUs capabilities with little programming costs. The following example normalizes the channels of a image before training, then it uses the transformed tensor as input to the model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Protein Profile with HMM</title>
      <link>https://dakerfp.com/post/protein_profile_with_hmm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dakerfp.com/post/protein_profile_with_hmm/</guid>
      <description>Profinling is the action of summarizing a set of data in a smaller mathematical model. One of the practical usages of profiling techniques is the classification of sequences. With a data set profile, you may calculate the distance of an instance to the model, and classify the instance trough this value.
Profiling proteins is a more specific case of profiling sequences. As we know from the previous post about Hidden Markov Models (HMMs) is a very robust mathematical model to represent probabilistically sequences.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>