<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Maximum Likeliyhood on Daker Pinheiro</title>
    <link>http://dakerfp.github.io/tags/maximum-likeliyhood/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Maximum Likeliyhood on Daker Pinheiro</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Daker Fernandes Pinheiro</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://dakerfp.github.io/tags/maximum-likeliyhood/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>CpG Islands (2) - Building a Hidden Markov Model</title>
      <link>http://dakerfp.github.io/post/cpg-islands-model-evaluation-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dakerfp.github.io/post/cpg-islands-model-evaluation-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By the definition of the CpG islands in the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://codecereal.blogspot.com/2011/05/cpg-islands-1.html&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;
and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://codecereal.blogspot.com/2011/05/hidden-markov-models.html&#34;&gt;Hidden Markov Models&lt;/a&gt;
(HMMs) short introduction, we now can model a HMM for finding CpG
islands. We can create a model very similar to the &amp;ldquo;Fair Bet Casino&amp;rdquo;
problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we are in a nucleotide of given DNA sequence there are two
possibilities, that nucleotide belongs to CpG island (lets denote state
S1) or do not (S0). If you analyse a sibling nucleotide it can stay in
the same state or to change with complementary probabilities. We can
view it as this Markov chain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://dakerfp.github.io/img/cpg.png&#34; alt=&#34;CpG states Markov chain&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the emissions of the states S0 and S1, we may have the associated
probabilities of the emissions of ACGT symbols. However we can&amp;rsquo;t know
for now how much are these probabilities. However if we have a dataset
of sequences with the attached information of where the CpG islands
occurs, we can estimate those parameters. I used these DNA
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cin.ufpe.br/%7Eigcf&#34;&gt;sequences&lt;/a&gt; tagged by biologists (used
&lt;a href=&#34;http://biopython.org/wiki/Main_Page&#34;&gt;biopython&lt;/a&gt; library to parse the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FASTA_format&#34;&gt;.fasta&lt;/a&gt; files) as the
training and test sets to build the model and evaluate the technique.
This dataset consists of nucleotides in upper and lower cases. When we
have a given nucleotide in upper case, it denotes that it is a CpG site
and the lower case nucleotides means they are not. I used a statistical
technique called &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maximum_likelihood&#34;&gt;maximum likelihood&lt;/a&gt;
to build the HMM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the maximum likelihood to calculate the HMM emissions
probabilities, I count each char frequency in the dataset and divide by
the total amount of nucleotides in the same state:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://dakerfp.github.io/img/cpgemissions.png&#34; alt=&#34;Emissions probability diagram&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;P(A|S0) = a / (a+c+g+t) P(C|S0) = c / (a+c+g+t)
P(G|S0) = g / (a+c+g+t) P(T|S0) = t / (a+c+g+t)
P(A|S1) = A / (A+C+G+T) P(C|S1) = C / (A+C+G+T)
P(G|S1) = G / (A+C+G+T) P(T|S1) = T / (A+C+G+T)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to calculate the transition probabilities of each state, count the
number of transitions between a CpG to a non CpG site ``(out_of) and
the reversal transitions (into). Then divide each of them by the state
frequency which they&amp;rsquo;re coming from. Note that the permanence
probability of each state is the complement of the probability of
transiting between states since there is no other state to go:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;P(S0|S1) = out_of / (A+C+G+T)
P(S1|S0) = into / (a+c+g+t)
P(S0|S0) = 1 - P(S1|S0)
P(S1|S1) = 1 - P(S0|S1)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our model is almost done, it just lacks of the initial transitions which
can be supposed to be the frequency of each state over all nucleotides:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;P(S0) = a + c + g + t / (a + c + g + t + A + C + G + T)
P(S1) = A + C + G + T / (a + c + g + t + A + C + G + T)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ghmm.org/&#34;&gt;ghmm&lt;/a&gt; to create my HMM with the given
dataset and it generated this model:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;DiscreteEmissionHMM(N=2, M=4)
	state 0 (initial=0.97)
       Emissions: 0.30, 0.21, 0.20, 0.29
       Transitions: -&amp;gt;0 (0.00), -&amp;gt;1 (1.00)
   state 1 (initial=0.03)
       Emissions: 0.22, 0.29, 0.29, 0.20
       Transitions: -&amp;gt;0 (1.00), -&amp;gt;1 (0.00)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to notice that when we print the HMM it says that has the
probability of 1 to stay in the same state. This occurs due to float
formatted print. The reality is that in that value is very close to 1
but still has a chance to hop between states. It&amp;rsquo;s also interesting to
see the probability of emission of C and G when we contrast the states.
In S1 the probability of getting a C or a G is significantly higher than
in S0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another manner of creating the HMM, is by initializing a model with the
same structure we modelled the problem and then apply some unsupervised
learning algorithms, such as the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baum%E2%80%93Welch_algorithm&#34;&gt;Baum Welch&lt;/a&gt;
algorithm. The Baum Welch uses randomized initial weights in the HMM and
once you feed untagged sequences, it tries to infer a model. However,
usually is far better initialize your HMM with biased data about the
problem (for example using the model we created) and let the Baum Welch
calibrate the probabilities. With ghmm do the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sigma = ghmm.IntegerRange(0,4) # our emission alphabet
emission_seq = ghmm.EmissionSequence(sigma, [0, 4, 5, ... ]) # create a emission sequence hmm.
baumWelch(sigma, emission_seq) # use a template hmm to calibrate the probablities
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next post I will show how is the evaluation process of the HMM
in the CpG island.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>